Hello! In this video, I will show you how
I solved a challenge from Alles
CTF created by a YouTuber
who you probably know - LiveOverflow.
The solution involves
multiple steps and make sure
to watch the video until the end,
because I used a method that allowed me
to get the first blood on the challenge
because I was able to exfiltrate the flag 95%
faster than the naive solution.
And that number is not a bait.
It's an actual calculation -
you will see for yourself.
If it's your first time here,
my name is Greg and here on YouTube,
I explain advanced hacking
techniques used in bug bounty reports.
I also have a podcast
and the newsletter, both free and paid.
To fully understand
my solution to the challenge,
you should first watch a video on
LifeOverflow's channel where he explains
how the challenge is built
and what are the components.
I will mainly focus on hacking it.
Right now click the card or the link
in the description to watch that video.
I think he's a guy that
doesn't need introduction,
but in case you missed it, he's a YouTuber
with over 600,000 subscribers
and over 300 public IT security videos.
There's a whole range of topics
covered from web security,
through CTFs to low-level
and even hardware exploitation.
If you are not subscribed or YouTube
does no longer recommend you his videos,
check out tons of free,
high-quality content.
Did you watch it already?
I hope, yes, so we can go ahead
with the walkthrough.
Let's quickly see
what the application does.
There are two separate directories.
First, I took a look at the app itself.
When seeing the source code,
I did not spend too much time
on those helper functions.
Instead, I went straight
down to controllers.
In most of them,
queries are executed
using prepared statements.
It means that the application knows those
parameters are not trusted and SQL
injection won't happen in them unless,
of course, there's a bug in the library.
However, in one function
there is a query created the unsafe way.
The prepared statement is used
but the order argument
is not a statement's parameter.
Python creates the string before
even calling query_db.
The function considers
this string as trusted,
including the order parameter
which is controlled by the user.
Every time there is just one place
where something is done
differently, is a good lead.
Of course, there is a chance that cheeky LifeOverflow planted this as a red herring,
but one way or another,
I had to check this.
I launched the application locally.
I quickly confirmed SQL injection
by using asc limit 0 and I saw no notes.
It meant that my limit clause
was present in the SQL
query and it returned zero rows.
Then I tried with the union.
However, I got blocked by web
application firewall.
At this point, I had to understand the
relationship between the two applications.
If you did watch
LifeOverflow's video you know it.
The crypter works like a reverse proxy,
and the app itself is not exposed.
I found that out
by examining contents of Dockerfiles.
Inside the source code,
there is only one controller
which forwards the requests to the app,
but before doing that,
the was_param function was called
on all the parameters.
Its logic was very simple.
It filtered only
a few words or characters.
Those included select, union and quotes.
It's a short list,
but it seemed quite convenient to me.
There was also no unusual things that
could open a way to more advanced attacks.
So I wanted to find a way to smuggle my
parameters without entering this function.
I spent some time here
by trying to find the bypasses
using those unfiltered values
like content-type header or cookie header,
but I didn't come up with anything smart.
Then I thought about
spending a bit more time
on the way those URLs are created.
Every time I see an address
just concatenated like this,
I feel like something might be off.
And I was right this time.
The path variable is a URL parameter.
There are no explicit transformations
here, but Flask automatically decodes it.
So if I used a path
with URL-encoded question mark,
then the request was sent
with the question mark decoded.
The reverse proxy didn't consider those
to be parameters,
but rather a part of the path.
So this way I was able to smuggle my
payloads, bypassing the WAF.
Note the ampersand at the end.
It's important because if it wasn't there,
the question mark would be treated
as the part of the parameter,
breaking my SQL query.
I confirmed that this bypass works
and I was ready to create the exploit.
I took a look into where the flag is.
It was added as the first note.
I wanted to use sqlmap for it
because it's much faster
when it comes to exfiltrating data,
but I couldn't configure it
to work with my specific case
where the payload was
the part of the path.
I didn't think creating tamper script
would help either.
Modifying the source code was an option
that I considered,
but they opted to write
my own exploit instead.
The first step is determining
what query to use to extract the flag.
Testing this on a running web app
would be very inefficient way,
even if it was running locally.
I would have to make additional effort
in order not to break encoding.
Instead, I took an advantage of the fact
that this is an open source task.
I just copied the database file
from the Docker container
and started testing different queries.
At this point, I noticed that there is
no plaintext flag in the database.
Instead, it's encrypted.
Considering the name of the challenge,
I could have expected this.
It was time to understand
the logic of this WAF.
Again, I was just briefly mention it in
the full explanation
is on LifeOverflow's channel.
I didn't find anything out of place
in generating a secret
or encryption/decryption functions.
What was interesting,
however, was that when ciphering,
the string ENCRYPTED:
was prepended to the content.
Most POST and GET params were ciphered.
Then, the decrypt
function took the whole response body
and deciphered everything
that had the string ENCRYPTED: prepended.
So my idea was to get the encrypted
input anywhere in the response.
Of course, it couldn't be in the note
because then it would
simply be encrypted twice.
However, there were some inputs
that weren't encrypted,
and those were very good candidates
for this purpose.
I quickly scanned the controller
for the presence of those
first three parameters,
but only so uuid used and in the redirect.
So I quickly dismissed the idea.
I thought, why not create an account
with the encrypted flag as the username?
And it did work.
I created a user
using the extracted, encrypted flag.
And what I saw after the login
was the flag from my local environment.
So I had the encryption
aspect taken care of.
Now, how to get this
encrypted flag out of the database?
At first I tried the simple union,
but it didn't work.
It was because Union mustn't be after
the order clause in SQL query.
So this is a blind SQL injection.
I couldn't use union,
but what I could do is a subquery.
That means that you can do
arbitrary queries to the database,
but you just can't
return them as the result.
There are many methods which you can use
to exfiltrate one bit at a time.
And if you can exfiltrate one bit,
you can exfiltrate
the whole flag after enough time.
My idea was to return ascending
or descending order using a subquery.
So I would check
if the first character of the flag is A.
If it was, my subquery
would return ascending.
If it wasn't, it would return descending.
In most SQL databases, there are functions
like if and substring
that will make it possible.
I could easily observe if
it's ascending or descending
by looking at the response.
If it was descending, then I knew that
the first character of my flag was not A.
So I tried to B, C and so on.
After I finally saw ascending order,
I knew the first character of the flag
so I could move on to the second one.
I would repeat this
until I got the whole flag.
Of course, this process is not manual.
The problem was I didn't find a way
to return ascending
or descending from a subquery
as those are not strings.
So then I started to think
what can be after the order clause.
The answer was the limit clause
which I used at the beginning
but then forgot about.
It tells the database
how many records we want to return.
I easily modified
my subquery to return 0 or 1 inside
the limit clause.
It did work locally.
However, it's a primitive solution.
It generates a lot of traffic.
For each character
of the encrypted and encoded flag,
I needed to send 64 requests
in the worst case.
Considering the output had the IV,
the ciphertext and the auth tag,
it could take very long.
I think the real flag
had about 200 characters.
If I were playing the CTF for points,
I would likely just leave the script
running for a few hours.
But I didn't. Instead,
I wanted to have a bit more fun.
So I decided to create
an efficient exploit,
especially that I saw that the challenge
was yet to be solved by anyone.
Usual tricks you can
use to speed up blind SQL injection
exfiltration are binary search,
which reduces it
to 6 requests per character,
using multiprocessing to brute force
many characters at once
or using regexes,
combining those two techniques.
But I knew I could do it
even quicker than this.
Considering that
we are in the limit clause,
we are not restricted to returning 0 or 1.
It can be any number.
My idea was to add
128 notes and return the amount of notes
equal to ASCII code
of the next character of the flag.
So when the first character was capital E
with ASCII code 69,
then my query would return 69 notes
because my limit clause
would be 69 as a result of this subquery.
To see what was the
value of the limit clause,
I could just count the amount of notes
in the response.
I did overcomplicate this part a bit.
Instead of counting notes,
I named them LIMIT0
to LIMIT127, which caused some boring
and annoying problems,
but I somehow dealt with them.
Finally, I successfully tested my script
on the local instance,
and I was ready to smash
the live environment.
My approach meant that I only needed
128 requests at the beginning to add notes
and then one request
per each character of the encrypted flag.
It meant that with 200 characters flag,
I only needed 328 requests.
That's a lot less than 1200 requests
of binary search
and 12,800 of native solution.
That's the worst case,
but even if we take half of that number
as an average complexity,
my solution was still 95% faster.
The server had some latency issues,
as probably many players were brute
forcing simultaneously.
But after some time,
I finally got the flag.
Thanks to the fact that I invested
a bit more time offline
to prepare my exploit,
I saved a lot of time online.
That's probably the reason why I was
the first one to solve the challenge.
If you enjoyed the video,
make sure to subscribe to the channel.
If you want to learn even more from me,
join my newsletter
and get the best hacking tips delivered
right to your inbox.
Sign up now for free
at mailing.bugbountyexplained.com.
For now, thank you
for watching and goodbye!